Dave Lotito

Data Scientist, Assistant Vice President

Professional Data Scientist at Citizens Financial Group with more than 3.5 years of experience analyzing large data sets and developing data driven solutions for Fortune 500 companies. Involved in various projects where I have led multiple teams to success.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Scientist, Advanced Analytics

June 2020 - Present

Citizens, Providence, RI

- Pioneered the development of the bank's inaugural OCR (Optical Character Recognition) machine learning model to facilitate the onboarding and migration of HSBC consumer banking customers. This innovative software proficiently extracted, predicted, and recognized characters, including letters and digits, from FDIC Trust Grantor Cover Sheets achieving near-perfect accuracy rates.
- Took a leading role in harnessing the capabilities of AWS Textract to facilitate the detection and analysis of text within documents. This strategic implementation played a crucial role in helping lay the groundwork for converting text into machine-readable output, resulting in a substantial contribution to the success of the Citizens' FDIC document compliance extraction initiative. This initiative involved processing hundreds of thousands of documents for the organization.
- Utilized strong problem-solving skills to address a batch of more than 1,000 missing documents crucial for the smooth execution of the LIBOR transition initiative. This effort not only improved the document retrieval process but also contributed to enhancing the accuracy and efficiency of our business operations during this critical transition phase.
- Managed the banks' consumer collections models, helping implement the various model control points needed to mitigate risk and identify issues.
- Created, improved, and maintained the LIBOR Sourcing python-based applications. Each day review Jira for user stories based on business needs and new requirements.

Business Strategy & Operations

May 2019 - August 2019

Fidelity Investments · Internship, Merrimack, NH

- Collaborated effectively within an Agile team, tackling diverse projects, and skillfully addressing intricate business analysis challenges within the PI / CCP framework to enhance customer service.
- Devised a comprehensive strategy by consolidating data, enabling the calculation of the distribution of financial advisor and relationship manager associates across Fidelity branches. This strategy proved pivotal in orchestrating the WIN10 / Outlook migration.
- Employed SQL proficiency to conduct a thorough analysis of both incoming and outgoing emails, resulting in the identification and resolution of communication routing issues among associates and clients. This initiative significantly streamlined communication processes.

CONTACT

- · Providence, RI
- 978-973-4253
- DavidJLotito@gmail.com
- www.linkedin.com/in/david-lotito
- · github.com/davelotito

SKILLS

Data Visualization/Engineering:

- Tableau
- Sisense
- Plotly
- Matplotlib

Techniques:

- · Hypothesis Testing
- Classification
- · Linear Regression
- Anomaly Detection
- Neural Networks
- Resampling Methods

Tools and Frameworks:

- AWS (SageMaker, Athena, S3, Textract)
- Python (Numpy, Pandas, Keras, TensorFlow, Keras, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Sklearn)
- R (ggplot, dplyr, tidyr, plotly, knitr)
- Databases (MySQL)
- Excel

EDUCATION

Boston University

MSc, Applied Data Analytics Boston, MA – September 2022 – May 2024

University of Massachusetts, Lowell

BSc, Management Information Systems & Marketing Analytics Lowell, MA – September 2016 – May 2020

CERTIFICATES

- Python for Data Science & Machine Learning
- Tableau Data Analytics & Visualization
- Advanced Deep Learning with Keras & Image Processing